Guide to the Abraham Lincoln collection, 1847-1864
The New York Public Library. Manuscripts and Archives Division.
Abraham Lincoln collection
1847-1864
1761
MssCol 1761
Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865
The New York Public Library. Manuscripts and Archives Division. Stephen A. Schwarzman Building Fifth Avenue at 42nd Street, New York, NY 10018-2788
1.5 linear feet (5 boxes, 1 v.)
Abraham Lincoln (1809-1865) was the sixteenth president of the U.S. Collection consists of original documents, photostats, facsimiles, and clippings concerning Lincoln. Papers include Lincoln's correspondence (some with generals in Union Army), notes, legal papers, military orders, and related items. Clippings are from newspapers and catalogs.
Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865
- Abraham Lincoln Papers
  - A. Original Manuscripts by Lincoln (in chronological order)
    - A. D folio (1 leaf). Deposition of Christian Goodman, 1842 August 16; 2 pages (Box 1)
    - Bill in chancery to Sangamon Co. Circuit Court, Illinois, Lincoln and Herndon as attorneys for Upton Crowl against John Grigg, David B. Ayers, Robert North, and William Parks. Affidavit sworn by Lincoln before J. Calhoun, clerk, and L. B. Adams, 1847 July 28; 4 pages (Box 1)
    - R. K. Webster against Gill & Rupert, 1852 April 9; 2 pages (1 leaf) (Box 1)
      Plea and notice filed April 9, 1852. Accompanying the document is a letter dated September 24, 1895 from Horace White to Mr. Eames; and a letter dated September 21, 1895 from Jesse W. Weik to Mr. White.
    - Plea and notice in case of Robert B. Courtney and others against Nelson Maddox, administrator of the estate of William T. Courtney, 1853 June 2; 2 pages (1 leaf) (Box 1)
    - To William Cullen Bryant, 1860 June 28; [Transferred from Bryant-Godwin Collection].; 1 page (Box 1)
    - Printed letter signed To the Governor of the State of Mississippi. Countersigned by William H. Seward, Secretary of State, 1861 March 16; 1 page (Box 1)
    - Postmark on envelope addressed to Parke Godwin, Esq. franked by President Lincoln, 1861 April 7 (Box 1)
    - To Lieutenant General Scott. [In separate slipcase], 1861 May 24; 1 page (Box 1)
    - document signed, Original order suspending the writ of habeas corpus between New York and Washington. Countersigned by William Henry Seward, 1861 July 2; 1 page (Box 1)
    - To the Honorable Secretary of War, requesting appointment of four officers to Kansas Volunteers, 1861 August 7; 1 page (Box 1)
    - Endorsed reply on autograph letter signed by Lincoln on from Major General George B. McClellan, 1861 August 16; 1 page (Box 1)
    - To Captain Thomas G. Pitcher, accompanied by blank envelope endorsed (on verso) by [Capt. Pitcher], 1861 August 22; 1 page (Box 1)
    - Letter, with envelope. To George Dad [...?] Written by John Hay under President Lincoln's direction, 1862 January; 1 page (Box 1)
    - To Major General McClellan, 1862 July 1; 1 page (Box 1)
    - To Secretary of War requesting appointment of John P. Sherburne as Assistant Adjutant General, 1862 July 12; 1 page (Box 1)
    - document signed, Commission to Henry C. Bowen as collector of taxes, 1862 August 22; 1 page (Box 1)
    - Autograph endorsement signed, 1862 August 22; 2 pages (Box 1)
      August 15, 1862 to Lincoln from Rear Admiral S. F. Dupont.
    - To Major General McClellan. Also, portrait of General McClellan, 1862 September 11; 1 page (Box 1)
    - document signed, 1 p. Authorization to Secretary of State to affix seal to "my proclamation of the additional article for the suppression of the African slave trade between the United States and Great Britain", 1863 April 22 (Box 1)
    - To William Cullen Bryant. [Transferred from Bryant-Godwin Collection], 1863 May 14; 1 page (Box 1)
    - To General Tyler, 1863 June 5; 1 page (Box 1)
    - To Major General Hooker, 1863 June 16; 1 page (Box 1)
    - document signed, Warrant for the pardon of Peter Snyder, 1863 June 16; 1 page (Box 1)
    - To the Secretary of War requesting statement regarding two men in Capitol Prison, 1863 September 15; 1 page (Box 1)
    - To Secretary of War requesting statement for mustering out of Col. George P. Ihrie, 1863 September 18; 1 page (Box 1)
    - To Major General Meade regarding pardon for John Murphy because of his age, 1863 October 12; 1 page (Box 1)
    - Document signed by the Governors of Ohio, Indiana, Iowa, and Wisconsin offering the Government 80,000 troops, 1864 April 21 (Box 1)
      With autograph acceptance by President Lincoln and by Secretary of War Stanton dated April 23, 1864.
      In separate slipcase.
    - Pardon of John Connor for desertion, 1864 April 22; 1 page (Box 1)
    - letter signed, To William Cullen Bryant. [Transferred from Bryant-Godwin Collection], 1864 June 27; 3 pages (Box 1)
  - B. Letters to Abraham Lincoln
    - from -? at Pittsburgh, 1862 September 3; 1 page (Box 1)
    - Henry W. Hoffman at Baltimore, On letterhead Custom House, Baltimore, Collector's Office, 1862 October 2; 4 pages (Box 1)
    - document signed Thomas Hoge, 1862 October 16; 1 page (Box 1)
    - John Rowe, at Gallipolis, Ohio, 1862 October 29; 3 pages (Box 1)
    - C. L. Leary, at House of Representatives, 1863 February 27; 1 page (Box 1)
    - J. W. Patterson, at Washington, 1864 June 14; 2 pages (Box 1)
    - Letter (fragment), 1862 September 27; 1 page (Box 1)
      from — -? At Lancaster, Penna, leaf. Note in another hand on verso.
  - C. Copies of Letters, endorsements, etc. by Abraham Lincoln
    - Photostats (negatives) made in, 1949 (Box 1)
      from originals in possession of R. E. Burdick (52 items in 2 folders).
- Darius Nash Couch Papers
  - Copies of telegrams to President Lincoln (Box 2)
- Thomas Addis Emmet Collection
  - Abraham Lincoln to William Henry Seward [EM #1465], 1861 April 18; 1 page (Box 3)
  - letter signed, Abraham Lincoln to Mary L. Booth. The body of the letter is in handwriting of John Hay [EM #11708], 1862 August 1; 1 page (Box 3)
  - Abraham Lincoln to E. C. Middleton. [EM #1469], 1864 December 30; 1 page (Box 3)
- Edward S. and Mary Stillman Harkness Collection
  - Receipt to T. R. Skinner for court fee. Stuart & Lincoln. [Vol. #12], 1840 January 21; 1 page (Box 3)
  - Bill in chancery filed in Sangamon Circuit Court in case of Thompson & wife vs. J. B. Broadwell. Logan & Lincoln for defendants. [Vol. #12], 1845 November 18; 1 page (Box 3)
  - Charles D. Nickles vs. James Wilson. Answer of James Wilson to bill in chancery against him in Circuit Court of Sangamon Co. Lincoln & Herndon for defendant. [Vol. #12], 1854 March 25; 3 pages (Box 3)
  - To H. D. Sharpe, at New York. [Vol. #12], 1858 November 9; 2 pages (Box 3)
  - Lincoln to J. S. Baker sending his autograph. [Vol. #1], 1860 December 17; 1 page (Box 3)
  - 1864 September 20, 1 page (Box 3)
    Autograph endorsement signed On verso of petition from "We the undersigned Union men". Countersigned by W. W. R [...?], clerk. A. note signed by J. B. [Henderson?] at bottom of page. Top portion of petition cut off. [Vol. #17].
  - Lincoln at Springfield, To H. D. Sharpe, Esq. [Vol. #12], 1858 December 8; 1 page (Box 3)
  - Photographic portrait of President Lincoln taken on the balcony at The White House, March 6, 1865 (Box 3)
    by H. F. Warren, Waltham, Mass. [Vol. #17].
- Josiah Gilbert Holland Papers
  - Copies of letters, 1843-1860 (Box 4)
    by Lincoln to Herbert Asbury, W. H. Herndon, and James F. Speed.
- Lee Kohns Memorial Collection
  - Bill of Stuart & Lincoln in William Andrews against John Taylor, [circa 1839]; 1 page (Box 5)
  - document signed, folio. Answers to interrogatories in Martin Ruble against George Cashman in Circuit Court of Tazewell County, Illinois, 1854 May 10; 3 pages (Box 5)
  - From James Meredith Reade, Jr. to H. Bendan, 1861 July 10; 2 pages (Box 5)
  - From J. F. Farnsworth to President Lincoln, 1864 December 21; 1 page (Box 5)
  - Lt. General Ulysses S. Grant, to President Lincoln. On letterhead Head-Quarters, Army of the Potomac. [In U. S. Grant folder], 1865 March 30; 1 page (Box 5)
  - Bill of Stuart & Lincoln in case of William Andrews against John Taylor, undated; 1 page (Box 5)
- Richard John Levy and Sally Waldman Sweet Collection
  - document signed, Appointing William B. Farwell as naval officer for the District of San Francisco. Also signed by Salmon P. Chase, Secretary of the Treasury. [In Box 1, folder 4], 1861 July 29; 1 page (Box 6)
  - From U. S. Citizens regarding Lincoln's death and end of the Civil War, 1864-1865; 3 autograph letter signed (10 pages) (Box 6)
    Also, political cover printed with Union Party slogans.
- Miscellaneous Papers - James Harlan
  - letter signed, James Harlan to President Lincoln, requesting appointment of Charles Williams as chaplain at Keokuk. Signed by James Harlan, James F. Wilson, and James W. [Grimes?], 1862 June 20; 1 page (Box 7)
  - letter signed, James Harlan To President Lincoln regarding appointment of Rev. Silas Rawson. Countersigned by A. Porter, 1862 (?) July 4; 1 page (Box 7)
  - James Harlan to President Lincoln transmitting application of Rev. Vernon for chaplain of Lawson Military Hospital, 1863 March 12; 1 page (Box 7)
- T. H. Morrell Collection
  - To Whom it may concern, is recommending William Johnson, a colored boy, 1861 March 7; 1 page (Box 8)
- Theodorus Bailey Myers Collection
  - Autograph endorsement signed, 1861 December 12; 1 page (Box 9)
    December 12, 1861 from Mr. Dunn at House of Representatives.
- James Polk Autograph Album, 1848-1849
  - Autograph signature (Box 10)
- United State Sanitary Commission Records
  - D. S., Order creating the United States Sanitary Commission, signed and approved by President Lincoln on June 13, 1861. Countersigned by Simon Cameron, Secretary of War. [Doc. #56262], 3 pages (Box 11)
  - Autograph endorsement of circular to the "Loyal Women of America". Countersigned by Winfield Scott [Doc. #2486], 1861 September 30; 1 page (Box 11)
- Ruth and Hermann Vollmer Collection
  - Autograph endorsement signed by Abraham Lincoln, 1861 September 2; on verso of autograph letter signed (Box 12)
    September 6, 1861 from John F. Potter to Lincoln requesting an army appointment for Mr. Helper of North Carolina.